[Music]
This is software engineering radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at se-radio.net.
SE radio is brought to you by the ITE computer society.
and by it e software magazine online at computer.org/software.
[Music]
Hello, this is Sriram Pam from Soft Engineering Radio.
Today with me I have Amay Desai,
CTO of Nexla and we'll be talking about the model context protocol or MCP. Welcome to the show Amay.
Hey Shiran, glad to be here.
Before we dive in, you want to tell us about yourself and Nexla?
So I am Amay.
I am CTO of Nexla and Nexla is a data integration platform that allows anyone to move,
connect, transform data using no code as well as low code processing.
Over the last 18 months, we have also built agentic AI systems using MCP as well.
as not MCP to help people with the data problem and specifically the data engineering problem.
And before Nexla, I've worked at both kind of small and big companies.
But I've largely been with let's say data systems as a problem for the last part of a. good decade.
Did machine learning before it became deep learning and now before it became kind of let's say LLM.
Thank you. Exciting.
I'm glad you mentioned MCP because that's what we're talking about today. Let's dive in.
In last 18 months, 2 years LLM have taken over and MCP is the latest thing.
What actually resulted in today's world was MCP as in why MCP? What is MCP?
Good question.
To start off, I think what happened is post charge GPT having its aha moment,
everybody wanted to use it for pretty much everything.
And that was the promise of the Chad GPT cuz you could have a simple UI where.
you could ask it questions and it would do impressive things whether they were right or wrong.
And one of the key things and people as they started incorporating large language models into software just.
building software there was a lot of.
scaffolding I would say spaghetti code that started getting written.
when integrating to variety of different data systems tools APIs call it may.
and anthropic came out with model context protocol protocol being the key word for how LLMs should connect.
to external data sources and tools.
So it's a standardization that I think MCP brought to the table.
and that helps a lot in I would say software engineering and agentic system today.
and that's not just relevant to MCP but a few other protocols that have come out.
but MCP I would say is the cleanest protocol and the simplest protocol that we have today.
So before MCP how were these integrations happening?
I believe there were tools what was the state of the world there?
I think what was happening before was people were using a variety of open-source packages as.
well as rest APIs and quite a few langstack llama index or whatnot.
and using those packages to writing the LLM part of the code.
which is the I would say the sexy part. and then there was I would say the harder part.
which is how do I communicate to a variety of different data systems.
So you would go and explicitly write code for talking to APIs, managing credentials and all of those details.
and how do you want to also embed those APIs with the LLM calls.
that the frameworks would allow.
This was making the problems I would say.
that people are trying to solve with LLMs a little bit more hard as.
now you were spending a lot more effort on just the integration part.
rather than the actual solving part of business logic.
This ended up creating a lot of I would say bad code, hard to test, hard to maintain, and.
hard to reason through things, which is.
where I think MCP at least allowed you a structure for how to do it.
And I think that's the difference right now between MCP versus what was there before MCP is.
that somebody can follow a structure to solve the same problem.
It still has its own pitfalls, but at least you start from a much better setting.
rather than a clean set of, hey, I have to just write code.
So getting a bit more of a visual framing of this before MCP developers would write code let's. say for.
example access their own internal things tools and so on right.
everyone was writing you would say custom connectors or custom glue logic by and large.
can you use example of one of these things like in a real setting we've all seen the.
get weather example on open AI space right?
no I think get weather is tool calling at it it's too simple. so what's a real world messy example.
so I think a messy example largely I would say as engineer would be GitHub API.
You have the GitHub API which you can do let's just simple analytics around how.
well your engineering team is performing.
whether that's in terms of number of contributions whether that's in terms of number of PRs that.
they have pushed out how many PRs got reverted how many was the number of lines of code.
that you would write.
these are five six seven different API calls for just one particular system and you.
need to write a lot of scaffolding custom code for how to make somebody like languin understand this.
with MCP it's more organized and as a construct available where you define it as.
a tool call and then can have the rest of the information relevant to the problem statement.
rather than integrating with pretty much everything under the sun that the GitHub API might need.
So that I think was a step change in terms of what developers are doing today. I think the other thing that is.
now getting to the forefront is using a lot of this framework you yourself needed to write an. orchestrator.
or how should those calls be called in.
either a chain or a sequence or in a conditional manner that only when kind of a finishes.
or rather let's say not a but get all the engineers information.
which is list users as a API call.
then for each user make an API call to get their contributions.
for each same user make another API call to say how many PRs did they reverted.
let's just stick with those three as an examples right.
I have now created a workflow for.
which I have written very custom code for the use case or the problem statement that I have.
which is I want to find out how my engineering team is doing just at GitHub as analytics.
now with MCP I can list down those three APIs as simple tool calls.
and then let MCP take over how to do the sequencing of those operations.
which is I think what the step changes the biggest step changes towards now.
is the sequencing being done by MCP or by the large language model that's optimized for MCP.
it's the large language model doing it.
but MCP is enabling that to be done in a coherent structured manner.
and you can reason through those things.
when I say reason through those things I don't mean LLM reasoning but as.
a software engineer you can reason through which call happened where whether there was access or not.
and whenever that call happened, what was kind of the response for it and the accuracy around it.
The alternative is you as an engineer is pretty much writing for every single API call,
scaffolding code around what was the response that.
came in, how do I parse that response, what happened when that response errored out.
If you think about like if you're familiar with Python,
you have to write try catch exception blocks for each of these API calls.
With MCP, you're relying on an LLM to do that for you,
which is a much easier way to build systems very very quickly.
So maybe if I can give an analogy, people previously were writing scripts to do this.
But with MCP, you can think of your problem solving more as a composition way of doing it.
And each MCP, you can think of it as a micros service or a AI or an API, an endpoint.
Correct.
which is much easier to scale purely from a latency and software engineering standpoint too.
So just to summarize and get a better visual picture of it before MCP your example of knowing.
which of your developers are I mean what the stats are you write three tools.
one for getting the developers getting their PR counts and then a third tool for summarizing it.
but then you would also write scaffolding to kind of target let's say open AAI to parse out.
that.
tool call information in one way in a different way in a different way.
but now with MCP you're saying that look all I have to do is provide my three different. tools.
and by the virtue of all supporting MCP you're kind of solving the multiplexing problem.
Correct. That's a good way to put it.
One other example if I could give Shirram is.
and this might make it a little bit easier is let's say.
you just want to create a Python script that convert JSON files on your file system to CSV.
and then you want to commit it automatically to a GitHub repository.
You can clearly use a framework to do this with LM calls.
and prompts to do the like JSON to CSV conversion part.
What you'll end up realizing is the prompt to do this is very small.
I just want to read whatever is there as a JSON data and convert it to CSV.
So if you let's say only have a JSON file with five keys.
and you want to convert that.
to a CSV with five columns, the prompt for that is barely four or five lines of code.
Okay.
But then you're writing a lot of code to read JSON files.
Ensure that the JSON files are read correctly.
Do globing.
ensuring that if it is nested structure that you can get through do iteration on it.
do the same thing for generating new CSV files.
and writing them out correctly maybe in a directory structure similar to what you had with JSON files.
and then you're now writing code to also do committing it to the GitHub repository where now you.
need to handle OOTH and a lot of other things around GitHub as.
well as the file system piece.
you can register all of these as tools with MCP and then let the LLM take over.
and with the LLM's intelligence a lot of.
that call it scaffolding code call it spaghetti code.
but just the integration code is erently being handled by LLM.
which makes the amount of work you're doing much less which makes the amount of work you.
have to reason through just because now you're looking at lot less lines of code much easier to.
manage.
and this there is an assumption here the assumption is.
that the LLM is strong enough to do all of this.
if the LLM is not strong you pretty much are like going to fail.
and MCP showed with better models this is a phase where we are getting closer and closer to-
that's a very good point right about LMS having the capability to orchestrate MCP.
right taking a lowweight model you know may not be as effective in this right.
so how did the LMS themselves have to evolve to actually be more aligned with MCP.
I think one of the key unlocks that happened for MCP to get where.
it is is the reasoning capabilities of LLMs and LLMs themselves having at least baseline reasoning capabilities today.
if MCP would have come out when charg 3.5 came in like late 2022, it wouldn't have succeeded.
The framework itself wouldn't have led to good outcomes.
So the fundamental thing that I think changed is that models have gotten better.
and the what we have realized over good amount of 2024.
and 2025 is models are going to continuously get better.
There is this whole construct of we have trained on all the data of the world.
and synthetic data is being used now to make the models better.
The contrarian argument to that is deepseek.
which came up with a new architecture for thinking with gRPO.
that allowed that model itself to get better.
So the language model as the orchestrator improvement has enabled MCP to get where it is.
The other part that I think MCP did is a lot of very good software engineering work in.
terms of the protocol that is established which is JSON RPC 2.0.
that allows it to have very strong interoperability across vendors,
agents, runtimes, file systems and all of those things.
So that is the collection of I would say the as a system architecture.
that what model context protocol laid out that has made it go ahead.
and I think this might be a hot take.
but I think of hallucination as a feature not a bug.
and I think that has started manifesting more.
and more in the last 12 months where people don't treat hallucination as a bug completely.
interesting how would one go about.
I mean this is off topic but how would one go about treating.
or exploiting its nature as a feature.
I think creatively if you want it to give you kind of more ideas and.
make problem solving with I don't want to say infinite space.
but a bounded space beyond three or four actions.
It's the capability of an LLM to hallucinate allows it to kind of explore.
that search space much better.
An LLM hallucinates cuz it is trying to solve problems with whatever information it has.
It is exploring search space to get to a particular resolution.
If you restrict that search space completely with let's say temperature equal to zero in.
which case also it does end up hallucinating and reasoning sometimes poorly.
still you're not going to be able to do the language model as a orchestrator at all.
You can only then do that for a few set of tools.
or a few set of functions which is exactly what OpenAI did with function calling.
you had your get weather API or get real the right time.
or add to numbers kind of thing, right?
And you would need to set temperature almost I would say to zero to get those tools to.
work correctly.
Even if you set it up to a little bit higher, it would kind of fail.
With LLM's getting better, that problem to a degree got solved and now allowing hallucination,
if you treat it as a feature, you can start getting into the orchestrator part.
because now it can start to think and reason, okay, here are some seven, eight tools that.
this engineer has put out for me or this engineered system has put out for me.
How do I go about trying out different combinations for them?
And if some combinations do end up getting wrong, that's okay.
This is going to be an acceptable path of being wrong.
and we'll be able to move on past that.
Certain domains won't accept this, which I think is fine.
and I think people are now clearly realizing that.
that if you're trying to do LLM stuff, let's say with rocket science where NASA or.
SpaceX is trying to send rockets up into sky with the humans lives at risk,
that's probably not a good idea, no matter how good an LLM gets.
But if you're trying to do just simplification of your workflows in your day-to-day operations or.
in the day-to-day businesses where you have where you don't have this much criticality involved,
hallucinating is kind of okay.
It's not the end of the world.
if 90% or 95% of my job is happening without me even needing to do it.
That's an interesting take because humans also hallucinate, right?
Correct. And it's a big part of how you solve problems, right?
I mean in your own dev engineering flow you're not just going down a single path.
that you know the exact answer for the depth first way.
and and you aren't exactly trying at every combination at every level the bread first way.
you're kind of doing a a star approach trying a few things here coming back try something else.
learn from it and so on. and that's kind of what's happening here too it sounds like.
and I think at least this is my take I think hallucination is hyped up.
and for like the dumbest examples that.
an LLM fails at it can't count how many hours are there in a strawberry.
or the I think is 9.1 greater than 9.9 that Karpati recently showed.
I think I want to say if you focus on the more impressive things it can do,
it can solve problems for you rather than the other way around.
I mean I'd rather the LM generate a string.
or character counter program rather than counting the characters themselves.
Mhm. Right. Thank you.
Going back to MCP and the Wise.
So traditional APIs we talked about JSON RPC.
but today there exists a very rich universe of API specs there's this is JSON RPC there's.
gRPC there's rest and so on right.
so if you look at the spec aspect of MCP what value is MCP adding over traditional APIs. from the specification point of view.
I think the number one thing I feel it has done is it is vendor neutral.
and you can say that the rest API is also using open API spec separately vendor neutral. Right.
Right. That is on the vendor neutral.
No, I think before MCP, I don't think LLMs are vendor neutral.
So with MCP, it established par with what everybody else had in the API land, which.
I think was an important table stake whether that was implicit or not happened by a side effect. I would say is orthogonal.
But ensuring that ended up getting people consistency.
that they can get the same set of responses or same set of reasoning at least. That's number one.
The vendor neutral aspect ensures interoperability which I think for a rest API also does exist but.
you do need to write a decent amount of again scaffolding code or to work with that.
The other part which I think is different than rest API.
and again I would say this is a side effect is it is open source.
It made people move all of their things also into the open source ecosystem.
it is easy to audit in terms of reviewing code and what you're kind of signing up for.
So as an engineer your work now is what exactly am I going to get from this endpoints.
and by only choosing the tools that you want you understand the explicit capability that is being granted.
if you go look at the GitHub API the rest API you have hundreds of APIs there.
that you may or may not care about.
but now when I'm trying to build a specific problem.
which is I need to convert this file and then just commit it to my GitHub repo.
I am understanding very explicitly that the capability granted to me is just.
that part of the problem statement.
While with rest APIs you can think of them more as another specification for a general purpose problem.
statement for anybody to solve any problem at hand.
While MCP now allows me to pick and choose what I need and do that very very quickly.
That I would say is kind of the difference in my mind at least around MCPS. and REST APIs as they have existed.
I'm going to drill a bit more into that.
Right.
So there is the aspect of exposing what you need which MCP requires you to do. Right?
Mhm. That's not a capability non-existent with APIs.
It's not what I was think trying to get at is I can only work on if.
I am a company today I don't need to build an API specification with hundreds of endpoints.
I can build a API specification with one single part.
and with configuration allow different code parts to happen.
MCP would allow me to also create my APIs now in a better way or.
in a more smaller/ concise way if that gets sense of what I'm trying to go there.
So here's maybe a categorical example I can give from our own work today.
where we have seen improvements come.
We as a data engineering company deal with directed asylic graphs tags right. It has a source node.
It has a sync node and it has a variety of transformation nodes that are there.
Each of these today has an API for our customers itself where you have the pipeline as.
an API, you have a source node API, transformation node API and a sync API.
Are the rest APIs or just general APIs?
No, the rest APIs and this is available on our like docs.nextloud.com.
So these are all resources that you expose as REST APIs.
Correct. But now I am in a place.
where I can just create one API within the configuration of that one API.
I can determine how things are going to go which is just the pipeline API let's say.
and if I say that the list of input to.
that pipeline API is going to be an array of nodes.
where the first and the last node can be kind of source and syncs.
and rely on an LLM to understand this basic construct very well.
and figure out what needs to happen as an execution item.
which is hey maybe just give me information about this node list particular pipeline.
or list just information about the sync that is present present in my pipeline.
Prior to MCP, we as a company built out five such APIs with get postport as three different. action verbs that we can do.
So amount of code that we needed to write was like.
if you look at the MVC controller pattern and things around that.
nature at least controllers as well as views.
and then the underlying database code for all of such five APIs for three different verbs.
and that is a decent amount of code.
It's like easily thousands of lines of code.
how I can do that with one API.
and if I make my specification reasonably well structured with 90%.
and this is actually happening live right now in our customer base itself that.
one API is able to do all the work.
rather than me needing to do five or six APIs.
and that one API is not calling all the other APIs that's the distinction I'm trying to make.
that one API has the right specification.
which we of course needed to rethink now that MCP enabled it.
but if I somebody wants to just get information The LLM orchestrator figures out exactly what to call. there.
So what is it calling at that point?
Underlying is just calling one function there which is still get put and post but.
all of those are just under one function.
that one object gets retrieved rather than me distributing the separating the object out right.
and at this point is this a wrapper then I mean almost like an N plus1 offering.
It's a N +1 wrapper which is correct.
but with a lot less artifacts for it to manage in terms of a codebase. if you are looking at it.
So the simplification is at the codebase level.
So for companies who want to do this you obviously have invested a lot in building out that.
service spec and the service implementations with the various verbs and so on.
But if you were to start today what would you do differently?
What would I do differently is I would just have one API call.
and within that rather we have this already now.
where which is we have one API call and within that one API call we have different functions.
that are going in places to extract or retrieve or make updates for.
the end user rather than separating them out as different nodes just.
because those are easier for people to reason through.
So let me try to think of maybe another example cuz I don't think this example is necessarily.
putting the picture in place.
What I think I'm maybe trying to get at is with APIs you have a very fixed nature.
and they're very static the way you define it.
With MCP you get dynamism as a first class feature right out of the gate.
and that makes building software very different than what we were doing before. Isn't that kind of contradicting our previous thing.
because you get dynamism but dynamis went to mix and match the tools that are already offered today.
That's what people have started with but what I'm getting at is I think MCP is reinventing how.
we are going to build software because of this nature.
Right.
So back to your example of how would you do differently?
What would that one MCP or the one all-in-one MCP API look like or tool look like?
I don't think it's an all-in-one MCP API,
but it's kind of more along the lines of instead of me needing hundreds of API endpoints,
I probably need somewhere along the lines of 10 to 15 public endpoints.
Correct? That's the distinction.
And that as a software engineer and.
if you're using MCP even to build software systems makes it I don't say much easier.
but it the amount of work you need to do is lot less.
which I think is going to make a step change in terms of just what you can do. with the rest of that time that you have now.
Of course I mean I think there's no doubt about the huge huge productivity boost just using cloud.
code and curs and hooking up with GMC tools right.
anybody who's saying otherwise I'm sure is there's a lot of reflection to be had there.
Yeah, thank you.
Thanks for clarifying where APIs end and where MCP begins. And I think you're right.
We are in a very early stage of how to actually build software in this new way.
Mhm. Now, obviously, you know, MCP's out there. Google came out with their A2A competing standards. What's happening there?
So, it was kind of interesting because I think Sundar had tweeted out to MCP.
or to not MCP similar to B or to not to B from Shakespeare.
and before I think the 2A kind of came out.
So you can think of MCP for a lack of a better word.
right now like as a vertical solution that I have this kind of specific verticalized problem.
I am going to solve this problem using MCP with tools,
resources and prompts and that's exist as a one single LLM call.
and you can of course combine them but as one single LM call.
A2A Google came out with which is agent to agent allows different agents even across different organizations to.
interact with each other and solve problems.
which is again like a fairly different architecture than what even we were capable of.
So you can now look at a company like GitHub,
Bitbucket and GitLab and you can make all of those talk to each other. The reason why this is kind of interesting.
and this is actually interesting for us as an organization is we do support on-prem deployments.
meaning our SAS tack can be deployed in our customers clouds itself and that's not true for.
us but a lot of other companies now it's almost like table stakes today right.
so the same example that I gave you around engineering velocity etc that.
I'm trying to let's say compute I have engineers.
who are also contributing to my customers gitlab stuff to bit bucket stuff.
so that the private install is on sync etc.
So if I want to get a complete picture, I'll also need to be able to do that.
With MCP, I need to effectively write three MCP servers that can do this today.
With agent to agent, one for each company handling its own kind internal tooling. Is that right?
Exactly. And there is a multiplicative effect there, right?
One for each private in other dependent on how many they have, one for each private install.
Agent to agent kind of solves that piece of the problem. So from vertical, it makes it horizontal.
Okay?
And that's the big distinction that I have with I'm mentally as mental modelist when thinking about it.
It also has a few other interesting properties around agent cards.
I think of it more as agent rumés.
where maybe you can figure out what is the capability of this agent.
whether it can capability in terms of the reasoning capability as well as how will it stream updates,
how it's going to negotiate all of that machinery.
And Google did make a pretty good effort in solving the security problem.
also when two agents can talk to each other.
If you figure out from the protocol how to set all of those pieces up.
The hot take I have is the reliability of agent to agent is much much less than MCPS.
because it's just standard distributed system probabilistic math.
I think a lot of people when they think about let's say the SLA numbers right 99.99999.
and so on so forth.
if you have one system that gives you 99.999.
and you make a distributed system out of it your SL numbers actually goes down just.
because of like standard probability there with expectation.
and if you have this across n things you can actually go down to number as 60.
and 70%. Unless you have replication and all of that. Exactly.
All of that machinery. Right.
So agent to agent is literally like I would say trying to do that right now.
And I think it's a very very hard thing to get right because of just that reason alone.
that how confident can I be that the GitLab agent that somebody else has built is like.
very very good if I don't even like get to see what is done there.
You're talking about availability, right?
And SLOs's from availability perspective.
I think before even that what about correctness now.
that you have different agents performing different things how can you be sure.
no that's what I meant from a reliability standpoint I meant by correctness that.
how do I know that that agent to agent thing is actually even going to work correctly.
like I almost have to try receive run and it's almost like with MCP I can unit test.
with agent to agent I have to do integration testing right.
and it is just a much harder problem to do.
Mhm.
So agent to agent I mean you're using A2A to orchestrate across multiple MCP.
we actually are not we tried it and we were not the reliability was too weak.
so we did not spend too much effort into that right.
and what was causing the low reliability were there any general patterns or-
well there I think two main things with MCP it is open source.
so it's a little bit easier to reason.
why agent to agent is not necessarily completely open source like KPMG as an agent.
or Accenture as an agent I just don't have access to it.
So the only thing I have is whether it works or not.
And if it does not work 70% of the times,
it's very hard for me to build a software system or business around it.
So that's the only data point that we have.
that whether it works or does not work from an abstraction perspective when just for layman like myself.
How would A2A differ from yet another agent orchestrating between two agents?
It doesn't in that sense.
There's a little a lot of machinery there.
which is around the agent cards aspect and the structured task objects that A2A has.
So Google introduced this notion of kind of agent cards.
where effectively you're writing textual description of what a particular agent does.
and it relies on you now as a whoever is building a particular agent system here to define.
that agent card in a well structured manner.
and you're trying to write that in a much more generic way.
cuz you don't know what exact problem might be thrown at you.
but you know the capabilities roughly of what you have but you're still you have to be generic.
You can't like be very very specialized cuz.
if you end up making it very specialized then you can't solve the general purpose problems there.
Almost like an MCP or a tool catalog.
Correct.
And in that way it allows you to at least give the impression.
that if you were to do this agent card, think of it as.
like you trying to hire someone and you get a resume,
you get a sign that whether this person is worth interviewing or not, right?
But whether that person will actually work or not,
you kind of need to go through the interview process, hire them.
and see them work for maybe 3 or 6 months and then you kind of know.
So that's the timeline you're actually looking at for an agent to agent protocol to give you.
a reasonable answer about whether it is going to work for a business or system or not. And that is very hard.
You could have a templated version of agent to agent for very specific problems.
where it can shine and work very well.
But then the flip question is then why not just use MCP.
if you're kind of breaking down a horizontal abstraction and making it templatized vertical itself.
That's where the simplicity of MCP in my mind wins.
right as a engineer building something it's much easier for me to build it.
I mean it almost felt like an N plus2 at this point.
I would actually say it's I think a little bit N plus N.
like if I could give you maybe an analogy it's.
basically how peer-to-peer communication with likes of Bit Torrent and Kaza was in late '9s and early 2000.
where if you I grew up in India.
so pirated movies were a big thing and it was all happening on such platforms.
and agent to agent is kind of going in that direction.
and whenever in India at least internet back. then was like really poor so if.
if you downloaded 70% of the movie and your internet crashed you lost the.
So the same thing is happening with agent to agent like it works well.
but then when it doesn't you kind of have to just gets completely unrolled.
and also the other interesting thing you mentioned about agent cards.
and agent resumes I suppose it's only a matter of time before we start seeing the sompics of. agents.
correct I think a lot of people have said this.
that we'll have managers like humans as managers of agents in the future. which I do think will happen.
maybe not to the level at which everyone's projecting right now.
But if I am managing an MCP workflow versus an agent to agent workflow,
like I know what one I want to manage today.
Yep. I mean, I'm sure they're going to have various personalities that you have to,
you know, train up for, right?
You know, in software, there's obviously standard design patterns and architectural patterns.
Are you seeing that in the MCP world?
Where are we in terms of patterns and what levels of maturity are they in today?
I think the standard I would say software pattern like we went to around like the peer-to-peer one.
which also kind of exist in MCP world if you want to create that definitely is there.
I think one pattern that we ourselves I think got a lot of mileage out of is the.
auction bidding pattern which.
I think is a little bit present in the ads world in terms of Google where.
the auction bidding to a level is you have a problem that you want to solve.
I actually give away a specific example.
Let's say I have a data labeling problem.
that we want to do on our data sets or on whatever data that we have right now.
Based on the type of data, I may want to use a different kind of labeling agent.
If the type of data is an image,
I can potentially use the image labeling tool or prompts that I have created.
For text, it might be that person. For audio, it might be a different agent.
For video, it might be a different agent.
And you might have a combination also of that the composition for it.
So, you kind of present this as a problem from your orchestrator,
which is like the LLM within the MCP world.
actually an orchestra that sits on top of your MCP world that.
hey here is a problem give me the information about how much will it cost you what would.
be the latency and what would be its accuracy.
could this be another MCP tool?
correct it's an MCP tool but with a very specific orchestration its objective as the only function. yes.
correct. right and then as a tool I can.
then start taking a decision okay this is what the task is this is what I got back.
now I can award the contract to the test specific MCP tool to go and execute on it.
And then it will report back me with results.
and I can then also take a decision about is the result meeting the contract that was given.
If not, I can also go and ask another tool that was there. Hey, can you do it?
You are like the second person who bid for it.
The first person has kind of failed.
This is why they failed.
Here is that's why I'm kind of choosing you right now.
This actually did help us do two specific problems at work in the last few months.
One was kind of the data labeling part, but the other one was building a PDF orchestrator.
You probably know that at this point unstructured data to vector database is like the bread.
and butter of data engineering for the LLM territory, right?
But the problem is people when they're working on hundreds of PDFs,
I think it's an easier problem when you suddenly get into enterprises with 100,000 PDF files.
If you run all of those 100,000 PDF files through vision LLMs.
or through high expensive LLMs like 40 etc. your LLM bills are really high.
like you're any spending anywhere between 25 to 50k just on processing 10,000 PDF files give.
or take 50-ish pages with images graphs and text around it.
But what you can do now here is you can for every page effectively make a decision.
Hey, this just looks it has pure text.
and some of the text might be formatted.
but open-source basic Python library call it PDF lumber or in the Java world.
I think there are many such libraries over years.
right now I think I'm forgetting the name of it.
I can just have that as a tool call I don't even need to use an LLM to. like.
understand a PDF either at a OCR level.
or at the vision level just like that basic thing works.
that also gives me cost efficiency it is also very latency efficient cuz literally doing this in process.
So this is one pattern that we I think were able to do with MCP really well.
and just I hopefully gets across that trying to build this as a system would take multiple quarters.
or at least when I was at Google it would take multiple quarters with very well-qualified engineers.
and teams to even get it right. But here now there are like a me.
and another engineer who have just built this out in like a matter of weeks.
which to us is like the remarkable part.
and of course it's not like that it is it works all the time really well.
but the fact that for me seeing what I had seen being built versus now.
what I can build the time difference is very very glaring and comes out very obvious.
I want to go back to the orchestration layer you had talked about just a few minutes ago. right?
How does the orchestrator evaluate the result from the different agents to know.
if it should make a different choice if it's acceptable or not?
It's a controlled problem that you need to do.
The controlled nature of that problem is two things.
One is prompts where you need to treat prompts as a specification as a software.
and then you also.
need to have a policy enforcement layer in addition to your prompts.
and that's how this orchestrator works pretty much.
But in your example, what was the metric for measuring that this agent's result was this?
Meaning post execution or pre-execution for like the reward assignment or after the execution is done.
Well, before the execution, right? Like you would get the result from one agent and you need to know how good it is.
It's interesting, right? So that is actually coming directly from the end user itself cuz the end user now can make. that decision.
What do they want to prioritize?
What is the trade-off that they want to do?
Do they want to see quick results?
do they want to see the best results.
or are they looking for a hybrid and kind of let us decide for that.
and the hybrid is kind of I would say the hardest thing to do.
We actually don't offer that as an option.
We make the user choose cuz a lot of people.
when they're trying to experiment they want fast results.
and then when they want to productionize they want the better results.
But when you're labeling you know terabytes terabytes of data right I think.
that is a little bit we at least haven't had terabytes of data.
I think a lot of people today in today's world are trying to generate fine-tuned data sets.
which largely are around like 100,000 samples. It could still be a terabyte especially.
if you have video or audio data but the number of samples is much less.
I think the terabyte number of rows like billions of rows was a problem I think 8 n.
years back when people are trying to build the systems.
Now that those systems are built the volume of the labeling actually has been very different.
Interesting. So the user is still involved in kind of providing hints around.
Yeah. Yeah. This is definitely human in the loop system.
It's not a autonomous system.
I don't think MCP or non MCP we are at.
that stage where you can have an very good agentic system that is truly autonomous. You need a human in the loop today.
And I think you're going to require human in the loop for at least another decade. if not more.
So what was the end to end calendar time for one of these steps to kind of happen.
in in that in that system you described before?
the entire thing that I let's say described in terms of choosing execution to happen for.
the PDF orchestrator for example for 10,000 files it took about one and a half day.
okay and how many human interventions were in there-
I think for one specific enterprise customer in the asset management space there were about four human interventions. for this entire thing.
that's pretty good that's pretty good. and the four human interventions were kind of largely around the orchestrator.
and the LLM itself kind of recognize different kinds of patterns that each file I'll have.
they are also learning from some of these patterns of files.
and the four patterns there were just two diverse.
it's not like for every little diverse pattern it makes a interaction with the human but for when.
there is two diverse there is this notion of you can say confusion matrix.
where is this like not something that you can solve by yourself.
and that is when you engage the human.
the interesting part here is building this orchestrator.
so we kind of build this orchestrator on top of MCP.
and using MCP you have to use LLMs you have to use policies.
but you also have to build just status quo machine learning models. which are going to help with such decisions.
Y and that I think is the culmination of how all of this works well together.
My next question was you know how did you come up with the confusion matrix.
because even with 100,000 files it's a lot sample. So were you sampling it?
Were you? no initially we would we would have a sample run for sure because this is like.
a folder structure right the folder structure has basically 10,000 files.
and you immediately get all the file names.
So you can very quickly random sample.
and actually this is where LLMs are uh very impressive if the everybody writes good file names.
Nobody writes file names as 1.
PDF 2 PDF especially in enterprises where things are written out.
well using those names itself a human itself can like.
infer what are potentially the diversity of data that might be there and so can an LLM.
So the random sampling now is actually a much more intelligent random sample.
There is this construct in CS which is called as importance sampling.
and important sampling was largely probabilistic based like when the algorithm was created.
What we are saying is to going forward importance sampling is.
where importance is determined by an LLM for a problem where it can do that.
and determining the importance of a file.
or diversity of data can be framed very easily because it's a text problem.
You know it's funny because typically prels premcp the engineering instinct was give entities like ids like 1.png.
as you said right 2.png 3.png PNG, right?
Mhm. And I think having actual names on the file names is a very important signal.
that LLMs have learned to exploit pretty effectively.
And I think there is a very good flywheel effect of this.
Now, if you're using LLM to output also such things, we are going to output sensible things.
Yes. Yes.
It's almost like we're returning to clean naming.
I think naming as a hard problem is getting solved right now. Right.
Correct. Moving on, I want to talk about enterprises. I mean MCP is is fantastic.
You know I think that every day you see a lot of new advances coming out from startups.
and from you know agile moves right.
enterprise what are the adoption challenges hurdles.
first of all I'm assuming there are challenges how are enterprises doing MCP today. and uh where can they be.
I think enterprises as a whole are struggling to do MCP today that's number one.
number two I think the struggle is by.
and large around the operations around the MCP servers rather than MCP itself itself.
cuz the def facto model when MCB came out was hey here is a GitHub repository check out.
run it on your local laptop with.
clot cursor and whichever kind of MCP host/mcb clients would support.
and that's kind of the end result that you get.
so it was still kind of very much based on in a local machine setup. now we have a bunch of new work.
that has happened which has allowed people to do this at the server level.
and it has kind of simplified that.
but one of The weaknesses of MCP protocol is by and large the security aspect around it.
So prompt injection MCP to some level gets prompt injection on steroids.
where now you can do command injections within your MCP to do tool calling in a adversarial manner.
So like I gave you the example of file system.
right hey read this JSON files convert it to CSV.
So now I have opened my file system via MCP to my users.
Now somebody can go and do whatever they want.
file systems have commands.
Most LLMs know how those commands should run.
I can just go and do RM minus RF star and that's it.
Like now you're completely messed up.
Or build a tool that does that to kind of segment a clear RM calling.
Exactly. So I think that is a big issue.
that people are trying to address and that is not a AI engineering issue.
It's a core I would say software engineering issue.
So the problem that I think enterprises are thinking about is some of this limitations of AI are.
also going to be solved by AI.
and they try to solve it via AI and it doesn't work.
and what we are trying to kind of get them to with our experience.
and address is some of these problems are actually not for LLMs to solve.
They are to be solved by engineering companies.
and companies like ours and a lot of other companies in the market right now.
and us solving them would help you get MCP kind of generate return of investment in a safe.
secured governed manner.
I think the adoption is happening.
It's the scalability across the organization is what is not happening today because of such concerns.
and also the MCP is still very easy to get started for engineers.
It's not very easy to get started for a non-technical person. Imagine a person who's a SDR.
If you ask them, hey, why don't you to GitHub for this Salesforce MCP server.
and then you can kind of just start talking to it.
It takes them I've seen people succeed at it,
but it still takes them a couple of days to know, okay, what is MCP.json?
What do I give it there? Where do I put it in cloud?
Just kind of solving the software part.
So an onboarder of MCP is kind of what is missing for the nontechnical audience today.
And keeping up I think there's a little bit of FOMO that if.
I don't get the latest version am I missing out on a feature.
that others have or my other competitors.
and those get harder decisions because if you don't have it's like you're trying to do software version. upgrades right.
and now you're trying to do software version upgrades with like FOMO inbuilt into it.
which was never the case before.
people were very thoughtful about doing upgrades cuz they don't want to break what is already working. while right now it's almost the other way around.
where you want to get onto the latest.
because the latest is going to make things better by default.
but it is going to also break your stuff.
and you don't know how it would break at all to some level as a non-technical person. while an engineer can control that a little bit better.
well I mean talking about security you know prompt injection for example it's still I mean yes it.
can be a software problem.
but it is largely an AI problem or rather it's actually exacerbated by you know reliance on prompts.
correct but I think prompt injection will be nonAI problem over time.
or will get solved with nonAI technology.
how so? I don't know yet I don't think anyone has cracked it yet.
but trying to solve the prompt injection problem via variety of techniques.
that we have done even actually evaluation for.
that matter with variety of techniques that we have done like LLM as a judge they don't solve.
the problem.
I they give you a perception or an impression of solving the problem but.
it is going to require rethinking some of the how we have built some of the system.
it's like how homorphic encryption or some of these other techniques came out for the problems that.
came last in the last 10 20 years that's what AI has brought to the table now. and I I don't know of any.
but I'm pretty sure in academic circles there are a lot of people working on this to solve. it without AI.
and I think that's where the unlock is going to come.
are there any insights that are pointing in this direction or are they still based on hope?
I think right now there's a little bit of hope more than insights.
that at least from my perspective more other people might have but I don't know that yet.
It's also because they have not been focused on that as a problem statement.
Right now we are still in the breaking phase. So right.
what about the other traditional security problems like access management rules and authentication?
Where and why do MCPs lack today and what can be done?
I think the protocol itself is lacking.
that information and there's a lot of work going on. right now to add those things to the protocol.
There are a couple of proposals that have been put out like similar to RFC.
but nothing yet has manifested.
I expect that to happen over the next year or couple of years actually but.
at least it's going in the right direction that people are thinking about this problems today.
But no one has solved it yet.
everyone's in the process of framing the problem very well and then kind of going.
because just the mention around access control.
and everything as a generic statement is I think fairly obvious that we need to solve it.
but what does that even mean in an MCP world I think is getting figured out as people. use MCP more and more-
are there any open almost like formal specification of these challenges that?
I believe so I don't know off the top of my head.
but I remember it off the top of my head right now.
but there are a couple of proposals that I have seen in the community around this-
what do you see would be challenges for authentication on the MCP world that are new compared to?
I think it's going to be more around the friction aspect about it.
like if you introduce some of the solutions.
that I think people have pushed forward right now do you sacrifice the adoption curve right.
and that's I think the hard part right now.
and which is why I think there's a lot of resistance from the AI engineering side.
that no I want people to use my tools right.
Even if it comes at a little bit of risk which is a little bit shortsighted.
I think that's where the challenge is largely going to be.
I guess you don't want the AI user running for the TFA two-actor authentication every time there's a. new completion. Right.
Correct. Even if you take an example of like someone like Zoom, right?
They just went on the Mac.
They sidestepped all of the security issues so to say with a Mac app.
They were able to get a lot of users while like Google Hangout,
Microsoft Teams have all of this proper authentication built in.
But adoption became a thing.
Now adoption is a thing for them.
It was not when Zoom kind of just went up.
Having said that, I think there are certain problems that I think definitely we need to solve. Maybe let me talk about the specific ones, right?
Like one is just like oath tokens.
Token theft is going to become a thing.
if especially if you're using MCP servers to.
because everything all if you're talking to all you're doing is APIs.
Either you're exchanging API keys or you're exchanging oath tokens.
So if you set up the right tool,
somebody can potentially abuse that tool to almost make a man-in-the-middle attack to do token theft.
And I think there is a work that is being put.
The most basic thing here is we should encrypt tokens at rest.
We should use shortlift credentials.
We should rotate any kinds of tokens regularly and just like isolating servers part.
So these are the things that people are just adding to the specification right now.
and then everybody will be able to implement it much more easily.
So in other words, catching up to standard security practices.
Correct. That's not so the prompt injection problem is kind of what I was trying to get at.
Right. Right. I think that I don't know how we'll solve,
but definitely there is a it's a open green field space right now.
Right.
I think back in 2008 it was there's an app for that. Now there's an AI for that.
I hope there is not an AI for prompt injection personally cuz SQL injection did not need AI, right?
to solve.
I mean it's not completely solved still.
but still at least it's better than where it was when it came out.
it needed SQL then right.
in next life itself what are some of the security challenges you're kind of prioritizing and focusing on-
I think outside of the MCP world one of the key challenges we have run into are two. problems.
one is around chunk level ACL especially in the whole vector databases brag deep research style problems.
where how do you have chunk level ACL.
which is pretty much what role level ACL in SQL databases at chunk level ACL for the document. databases?
That's number one.
And I think the number two problem is there is the security delegation problem.
which is and here is what I mean by that.
People who use Nexla and any APIs and any connectors,
any data systems today, they typically have a credential.
that opens up the pipes to be able to access data.
That gives you in my mind purely authentication and opens up the pipes.
But then there is an authorization layer on top of it.
which is I might open the credential to my SharePoint system.
but within my SharePoint system every file has its own access control whether a user can access it. or not.
And that is true across Salesforce for Salesforce objects. It's true across service now.
It's true across every system that you have today cuz every system has a access control system under. the hood for it.
How do you do this correctly is question one. How do you do this efficiently? I would say is kind of question number two.
and these are the two I would say maybe nonMCP but very much relevant on how do you.
get the right data with the right access to MCP as a problem statement.
that we are trying to solve. right and how you doing I mean what's I mean can you share the progress can you share.
so we have since had like a access control system which is similar to Zanzibar.
which is something that kind of Google open sourced like a.
while back which is used internally within Google also?
what we are doing right now we also treat this as an integration ation problem.
Instead of integrating with the data system, now we to integrate with the authentications and authorization system itself.
That's kind of one piece of the puzzle.
We need user consistency across the systems.
Meaning am I at nexa.com and am I at say Microsoft.com need to be the same person.
So we need to ensure that the same user is available here.
So when they sign up the two-factor with the right email addresses.
and all of that should be done correctly.
And then we need to pull in effectively am I at microsoft.com.
and the access control information associated with that.
as metadata that's going to be associated with whenever they make a data pipeline.
And this is where actually I would say has been one of our strengths.
where we are not just saying data metadata is just the schema.
or the samples data pipelines and data engineering in general has a lot of operational metadata.
A lot of people think of it purely in terms of the crrons. and the schedules of the world.
But it's this access control thing.
Who has access to what till how much time?
When does that change?
Things around that nature is what we are solving right now.
And we actually already solved it for a bunch of our customers.
who are using rag in this manner with us.
It's not that we are guaranteeing we'll give you the most accurate answers or the best answers.
but what we are saying is we are going to have secured governed.
and answers that only you have access to and not anybody else.
So you know as we wrap up what advice do you have for enterprises?
I think the biggest advice I would have right now is ROI.
or return of investment by and large would come.
It's not evident right now potentially because of the dollar number going up,
but it's very much evident in the productivity boost that everybody else has.
So being a AI skeptic is like a 2023 problem.
You can't be an AI skeptic in 2025, 2026.
Quite frankly, there might be a bubble burst and all of that with because. a lot of people are solving a lot of problem.
and a lot of money is being thrown at it.
But this is effectively what the I mean I don't want to say what the internet did.
but the analogy here is the actual adoption of internet made physical stores become digital stores.
and that caused the difference in how our economy and everything else grew.
The same thing is going to happen for SAS kind of AI taking over.
So that I would say is an thing that's going to happen for a lot of the-
don't overindex on the hallucination and prompt injection as a problem.
Instead of that, focus on the access control, governance and security as problems that you.
need to get in the hands of your users.
or in the hands of your employees in a safe and secured manner.
so that you can still unlock a lot of value for them.
That kind of would be one and two.
And then maybe last three is a sheepish spiel.
Try our company out next.
We have solved a bunch of this problem including orchestration.
and security and governance for large enterprise customers across hundreds of internal employees for them.
Sounds good. What about our listeners?
I mean obviously our listeners are very excited about learning this.
How would you recommend they get started or advance their learnings?
I think if you're a engineer who's not working in AI,
think of spending 20% of your effort at least working with AI.
and that does not mean using cursor.
but it actually I would say trying to solve a problem using AI.
and see kind of where that would go.
Here is a very maybe a prescriptive example, right?
Everybody wants in software has to do releases.
The fundamental thing there is push code to GitHub,
start a build job, run integration test, maybe deploy it to a canary.
or staging pipeline, see it work well, and then deploy to production.
There are about six, seven steps here.
You can build an MCP tool for this in probably a few days to maybe a week.
If you have all the access tokens, etc.,
and all of that build this out and see how productivity shift it makes for you.
where instead of thinking about this eight things now you just give a command.
and then you come back and it is done?
these are the places where you want to use AI to simplify your life as an engineer.
as a non-engineer I think a lot of people can probably use AI in their day-to-day things around.
meeting summary and meeting transcripts and a lot of things around that.
but one thing that I would maybe kind of recommend think through is how can you-
Like let's say you have your manager, you have your CEOs.
Make your MCP tool or your chat GPD or claude.
Give them the representation of what that manager or the vision of that person is.
and see how you can help them manifest.
that vision and that can make a huge difference in how.
you work on a day-to-day basis operationally yourself for getting your work done.
Thank you. So it sounds like just embracing it,
experimenting with like scratching your own itch are key parts of it.
Yeah, pretty much. That was a great summarization.
No, no, no. You did all the hard work.
So before we close, any other advice?
One last advice would be things that look simple with AI,
give them a shot much more than things that.
are maybe not that simple and will take you a lot of effort to get started.
Simple things solve simple problems much easily and that gets gratification instantly.
Thank you, Amma.
It's been very, very, very insightful, engaging and fun. Thank you for being on the show.
Yep. Thank you. And to our listeners, this is Shiran Panam from Software Engineering Radio.
Thank you for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an educational program brought to you by it e software magazine.
For more about the podcast, including other episodes, visit our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on each episode on the website or reach us on LinkedIn,
Facebook, Twitter, or through our Slack channel at seradio.slack.com.
You can also email us at teamse-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio is licensed under Creative Common License 2.5. Thanks for listening.